In the previous video, we gave a
mathematical definition of gradient
在之前的视频中  我们给出了一个数学上关于梯度
(字幕整理：中国海洋大学 黄海广,haiguang2000@qq.com )
descent. Let's delve deeper, and in this
video, get better intuition about what the
下降的定义 本次视频我们更深入研究一下 更直观地感受一下这个
algorithm is doing, and why the steps of
the gradient descent algorithm might make
算法是做什么的 以及梯度下降算法的更新过程有什么意义
sense. Here's the gradient descent
algorithm that we saw last time. And, just
这是我们上次视频中看到的梯度下降算法
to remind you, this parameter, or this
term, alpha, is called the learning rate.
提醒一下 这个参数 α  术语称为学习速率
And it controls how big a step we take
when updating my parameter theta J. And
它控制我们以多大的幅度更新这个参数θj.
this second term here is the derivative
term. And what I want to do in this video
第二部分是导数项   而我在这个视频中要做的就是
is give you better intuition about what each of
these two terms is doing and why, when put
给你一个更直观的认识 这两部分有什么用 以及 为什么当把
together, this entire update makes sense.
In order to convey these intuitions, what
这两部分放一起时 整个更新过程是有意义的  为了更好地让你明白
I want to do is use a slightly simpler
example where we want to minimize the
我要做是用一个稍微简单的例子 比如我们想最小化的那个
function of just one parameter. So, so we
have a, say we have a cost function J of
函数只有一个参数的情形 所以 假如我们有一个代价函数J
just one parameter, theta one, like we
did, you know, a few videos back. Where
只有一个参数 θ1  就像我们前几次视频中讲的
theta one is a real number, okay? Just so we can have 1D plots, which
θ1是一个实数 对吧？那么我们可以画出一维的曲线
are a little bit simpler to look at. And
let's try to understand why gradient
看起来很简单 让我们试着去理解 为什么梯度下降法
descent would do on this function.
[sound]. So, let's say here's my function.
会在这个函数上起作用 所以 假如这是我的函数
J of theta one, and so that's my, and
where theta one is a real number. Right,
关于θ1的函数J θ1是一个实数 对吧？
now let's say I've initialized gradient
descent with theta one at this location.
现在我们已经对这个点上用于梯度下降法的θ1 进行了初始化
So image that we start off at that point
on my function. What gradient descent will
想象一下在我的函数图像上 从那个点出发 那么梯度下降
do, is it will update. Theta one gets
updated as theta one minus Alpha times DD
要做的事情是不断更新 θ1等于θ1减α倍的
theta one J of theta one, right? and oh an
just as an aside you know this, this
d/dθ1J(θ1)这个项 对吧？哦 顺便插一句 你知道
derivative term, right? If you're
wondering why I changed the notation from
这个微分项是吧？可能你想问为什么我改变了符号
these partial derivative symbols. If you
don't know what the difference is between
之前用的是偏导数的符号 如果你不知道偏导数的符号
these partial derivative symbols and the
dd theta don't worry about it. Technically
和d/dθ之间的区别是什么 不用担心 从技术上讲
in mathematics we call this a partial
derivative, we call this a derivative,
在数学中 我们称这是一个偏导数 这是一个导数
depending on the number of, of parameters
in the function J, but that's a
这取决于函数J的参数数量 但是这是一个
mathematical technicality, so, you know
For the purpose of this lecture, think of
数学上的区别 就本课的目标而言 可以默认为
these partial symbols, and DD theta one as
exactly the same thing. And, don't worry
这些偏导数符号 和d/dθ1是完全一样的东西 不用担心
about whether there are any differences.
I'm gonna try to use the mathematically
是否存在任何差异 我会尽量使用数学上的
precise notation. But for our purposes,
these notations are really the same thing.
精确的符号 但就我们的目的而言 这些符号是没有区别的
So, let's see what this, this equation
will do. And so we're going to compute
好的 那么我们来看这个方程 我们要计算
this derivative of, I'm not sure if you've
seen derivatives in calculus before. But
这个导数 我不确定之前你是否在微积分中学过导数
what a derivative, at this point, does, is
basically saying, you know, let's. Take
但对于这个问题 求导的目的 基本上可以说
the tangent to that point, like that
straight line, the red line, just,
取这一点的切线 就是这样一条红色的直线
just touching this function and
let's look at the slope of this red line. That's
刚好与函数相切于这一点 让我们看看这条红色直线的斜率
where the derivative is. It says
what's the slope of the line that is just
其实这就是导数 也就是说 直线的斜率 也就是这条
tangent to the function, okay, and the
slope of the line is of course is just
刚好与函数曲线相切的这条直线 这条直线的斜率正好是
right, you know just the height divided by
this horizontal thing. Now. This line has
这个高度除以这个水平长度 现在 这条线有
a positive slope, so it has a positive
derivative. And so, my update to theta is
一个正斜率 也就是说它有正导数 因此 我得到的新的θ
going to be, theta one gives the update that
theta one minus alpha times some positive
θ1更新后等于θ1减去一个正数乘以α.
number. Okay? Alpha, the learning
rate is always a positive number. And so
α 也就是学习速率也是一个正数 所以
I'm gonna to take theta one, this update
as theta one minus something. So I'm gonna
我要使θ1减去一个东西
end up moving theta one to the left. I'm
gonna decrease theta one and we can see
所以相当于我将θ1向左移 使θ1变小了 我们可以看到
this is the right thing to do because I
actually went ahead in this direction you
这么做是对的 因为实际上我往这个方向移动
know to get me closer to the minimum over
there. So, gradient descent so far seems
确实让我更接近那边的最低点 所以 梯度下降到目前为止似乎
to be doing the right thing. Let's look at
another example. So let's take my same
是在做正确的事 让我们来看看另一个例子 让我们用同样的函数J
function j. Just trying to draw the same
function j of theta one. And now let's say
同样再画出函数J(θ1)的图像 而这次
I had instead initialized my parameter
over there on the left. So theta one is
我们把参数初始化到左边这点 所以θ1在这里
here. I'm gonna add that point on the
surface. Now, my derivative term, d, d
同样把这点对应到曲线上 现在 导数项d/dθ1J(θ1)
theta one j of theta one, when evaluated
at this point, gonna look at right. The
在这点上计算时 看上去会是这样
slope of that line. So this derivative
term is a slope of this line. But this
这条线的斜率 这个导数是这条线的斜率
line is slanting down, so this line has
negative slope. Right? Or alternatively I
但是这条线向下倾斜 所以这条线具有负斜率 对吧？
say that this function has negative
derivative, just means negative slope at
或者说 这个函数有负导数 也就意味着在那一点上有负斜率
theta is updated as theta minus alpha
times a negative number. And so I have
θ被更新为θ减去α乘以一个负数 因此我是在用
theta one minus a negative number which
means I'm actually going to increase theta,
θ1减去一个负数 这意味着我实际上是在增加θ1
right? Because this is minus of a negative
number means I'm adding something to theta
对不对？因为这是减去一个负数 意味着给θ加上一个数
and what that means is that I'm going to
end up increasing theta. And so we'll
这就意味着最后我实际上增加了θ的值 因此 我们将
start here and increase theta, which again
seems like the thing I want to do to try
从这里开始 增加θ 似乎这也是我希望得到的 也就是
to get me closer to the minimum. So, this
hopefully explains the intuition behind
让我更接近最小值了 所以 我希望这样很直观地给你解释了
what the derivative term is doing. Let's
next take a look at the learning rate term
导数项的意义 让我们接下来再看一看学习速率α
alpha, and try to figure out what that's
doing. So, here's my gradient descent
我们来研究一下它有什么用 这就是我梯度下降法的
update rule. Right, there's this equation
And let's look at what can happen, if
更新规则 就是这个等式 让我们来看看如果α 太小或 α 太大
Alpha is either too small, or if Alpha is
too large. So this first example, what
会出现什么情况 这第一个例子
happens if Alpha is too small. So here's
my function J. J of theta. Lets
α太小会发生什么呢 这是我的函数J(θ)
just start here. If alpha is too small
then what I'm going to do is gonna
就从这里开始 如果α太小了 那么我要做的是要去
multiply the update by some small number.
So end up taking, you know, it's like a baby step
用一个比较小的数乘以更新的值 所以最终 它就像一个小宝宝的步伐
like that. Okay, so that's one step
[inaudible]. Then from this new point
这是一步  然后从这个新的起点开始
we're gonna take another step. But if
the alpha is too small lets take another
迈出另一步 但是由于α 太小 因此只能迈出另一个
little baby step. And so if And so if my
learning rate is too small. I'm gonna end
小碎步 所以如果我的学习速率太小 结果就是
up, you know, taking these tiny, tiny baby
steps to try to get to the minimum and I'm
只能这样像小宝宝一样一点点地挪动 去努力接近最低点
gonna need a lot of steps to get to the
minimum and so. If alpha's too small, can
这样就需要很多步才能到达最低点 所以如果α 太小的话
be slow because it's gonna take these
tiny, tiny baby steps. And it's gonna need
可能会很慢 因为它会一点点挪动 它会需要
a lot of steps before it gets anyway
close to the global minimum. Now,
很多步才能到达全局最低点
how about if the alpha is too large.
So here's my function J of theta.
那么如果α 太大又会怎样呢 这是我的函数J(θ)
Turns out if alpha is too large, then
grading descent can overshoot a minimum
如果α 太大 那么梯度下降法可能会越过最低点
and may even fail to converge or even diverge. So here is what I mean. Let's say [inaudible]
ireful minimum So the derivative council
甚至可能无法收敛 我的意思是 比如我们从这个点开始
It's actually close to the minimum. So the derivative points to the right, but if alpha is too big, I'm gonna
实际上这个点已经接近最低点  因此导数指向右侧 但如果α 太大的话
take a huge step. Maybe I'm gonna take a huge step like that. Right? So I end up taking a huge step.
我会迈出很大一步 也许像这样巨大的一步 对吧？所以我最终迈出了一大步
Now, my cost function has got worse. cause it starts off from this value then now my value has gotten worse. Now my
现在 我的代价函数变得更糟 因为离这个最低点越来越远
derivatives, you know, points to the left, it's actually decrease theta. But look, if my learning rate is too big,
现在我的导数指向左侧 实际上在减小θ 但是你看 如果我的学习速率过大
I may take a huge step going from here all
the way out there so I end up. going all
我会移动一大步 从这点一下子又到那点了
there. Right? And if my learning rate was too
big I can take another huge step on the
对吗？如果我的学习率太大 下一次迭代
next acceleration and kind of overshoot
and overshoot and so on until you notice
又移动了一大步 越过一次 又越过一次 一次次越过最低点 直到你发现
I'm actually getting further and further
away from the minimum. And so if alpha is
实际上 离最低点越来越远 所以 如果α太大
too large it can fail to converge or even
diverge. Now, I have another question for
它会导致无法收敛 甚至发散 现在 我还有一个问题
you. So, this is a tricky one. And when I
was first learning this stuff, it actually
这问题挺狡猾的 当我第一次学习这个地方时
took me a long time to figure this out.
What if your pre-emptive theta one is
我花了很长一段时间才理解这个问题 如果我们预先把θ1
already at a local minimum? What do you
think one step of gradient descent will
放在一个局部的最低点 你认为下一步梯度下降法会怎样工作？
do? So let's suppose you initialize theta
one at a local minimum. So you know
所以假设你将θ1初始化在局部最低点
suppose this is your initial value of theta one
over here and it's already at a local
假设这是你的θ1的初始值 在这儿 它已经在一个局部的
optimum or the local minimum. It sends
out that at local optimum your derivative
最优处或局部最低点 结果是局部最优点的导数
would be equal to zero. Since it's that
slope where it's that tangent point so the
将等于零 因为它是那条切线的斜率
slope of this line will be equal to zero
and thus this derivative term. Is equal to
而这条线的斜率将等于零 因此 此导数项等于0
zero. And so, in your gradient descent
update, you have theta one, gives update
因此 在你的梯度下降更新过程中 你有一个θ1
that theta one, minus alpha times zero.
And so, what this means is that, if you're
然后用θ1 减α 乘以0来更新θ1  所以这意味着什么
already at a local optimum, it leaves
theta one unchanged 'cause this, you know,
这意味着你已经在局部最优点 它使得θ1不再改变
gets the update's theta one equals theta one.
So if your parameter is already at a local
也就是新的θ1等于原来的θ1  因此 如果你的参数已经处于
minimum, one step of gradient descent
does absolutely nothing. It doesn't change
局部最低点 那么梯度下降法更新其实什么都没做 它不会改变参数的值
the parameter, which is, which is what you
want. Cuz it keeps your solution at the
这也正是你想要的 因为它使你的解始终保持在
local optimum. This also explains why
gradient descent can converge the local
局部最优点 这也解释了为什么即使学习速率α 保持不变时
minimum, even with the learning rate Alpha
fixed. Here's what I mean by that. Let's
梯度下降也可以收敛到局部最低点 我想说的是这个意思
look at an example. So here's a cost
function J with theta. That maybe I want
我们来看一个例子 这是代价函数J(θ)
to minimize and let's say I initialize my
algorithm my gradient descent algorithm, you know,
我想找到它的最小值 首先初始化我的梯度下降算法
out there at that magenta point. If I take
one step of gradient descent you know,
在那个品红色的点初始化 如果我更新一步梯度下降
maybe it'll take me to that point cuz my
derivative's pretty steep out there, right?
也许它会带我到这个点 因为这个点的导数是相当陡的
Now I'm at this green point and if I take
another step of gradient descent, you
现在 在这个绿色的点 如果我再更新一步
notice that my derivative, meaning the
slope, is less steep at the green point when
你会发现我的导数 也即斜率 是没那么陡的
compared to at the magenta point out
there, right? Because as I approach the
相比于在品红点 对吧？因为随着我接近最低点
minimum my derivative gets closer and
closer to zero as I approach the minimum.
我的导数越来越接近零
So, after one step of gradient descent,
my new derivative is a little bit smaller.
所以 梯度下降一步后 新的导数会变小一点点
So I wanna take another step of gradient
descent. I will naturally take a somewhat
然后我想再梯度下降一步 在这个绿点我自然会用一个稍微
smaller step from this green point than I
did from the magenta point. Now I'm at the new
跟刚才在那个品红点时比 再小一点的一步
point, the red point, and then now even
closer to global minimums, so the
现在到了新的点 红色点 更接近全局最低点了
derivative here will be even smaller than
it was at the green point. So when I take
因此这点的导数会比在绿点时更小 所以
another step of gradient descent, you know, now
my derivative term is even smaller, and so
我再进行一步梯度下降时 我的导数项是更小的
the magnitude of the update to theta
one is even smaller, so you can take
θ1更新的幅度就会更小
small step like so, and as gradient descent
runs. You will automatically take smaller
所以你会移动更小的一步 像这样 随着梯度下降法的运行
and smaller steps until eventually you are
taking very small steps, you know, and you
你移动的幅度会自动变得越来越小 直到最终移动幅度非常小
find the converge to the to the local
minimum. So, just to recap. In gradient
你会发现 已经收敛到局部极小值 所以回顾一下
descent as we approach the local minimum,
grading descent will automatically take
在梯度下降法中 当我们接近局部最低点时 梯度下降法会自动采取
smaller steps and that's because as we
approach the local minimum, by definition,
更小的幅度 这是因为当我们接近局部最低点时
local minimum is when you have this
derivative equal to zero. So as we
很显然在局部最低时导数等于零 所以当我们
approach the local minimum this derivative
term will automatically get smaller and
接近局部最低时 导数值会自动变得越来越小
so gradient descent will automatically
take smaller step. So, this is what
所以梯度下降将自动采取较小的幅度
gradient descent looks like, and so actually
there is no need to decrease alpha
这就是梯度下降的做法 所以实际上没有必要再另外减小α
overtime. So, that's the gradient descent
algorithm, and you can use it to minimize,
这就是梯度下降算法 你可以用它来最小化
to try to minimize any cost function J.
Not the cost function J to be defined for
最小化任何代价函数J 不只是线性回归中的代价函数J
linear regression. In the next video,
we're going to take the function J, and
在接下来的视频中 我们要用代价函数J
set that back to be exactly linear
regression's cost function. The, the
回到它的本质 线性回归中的代价函数
square cost function that we came up with
earlier. And taking gradient descent, and
也就是我们前面得出的平方误差函数 结合梯度下降法
the square cost function, and putting
them together. That will give us our first
以及平方代价函数 我们会得出第一个机器学习算法
learning algorithm, that'll give us our
linear regression algorithm.
即线性回归算法
【果壳教育无边界字幕组】翻译：10号少年  校对：Femtoyue  审核：所罗门捷列夫